

# Soohwan Kim

#### ALRESEARCH ENGINEER · SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

6-10, Seokye-ro 13-gil, Nowon-gu, Seoul, Rep. of KOREA

□ (+82) 10-4564-4668 | 🗷 kaki.brain@kakaobrain.com | 🏕 blog.naver.com/sooftware | 🖸 sooftware | 🛅 Soo-hwan

"Step by step goed a long way"

## Summary.

Current AI Research Engineer at Kakao Brain. I majored in Electronic & Communication Engineering and minored in Data Science at university. My research interests include technologies for human-machine interaction, such as automatic speech recognition, speech synthesis, and natural language processing. I enjoy software development and sometimes like to write my knowledge or thoughts. I want to be helpful to others through open source. You can check my github (http://github.com/sooftware) to see what I am currently up to.

## **Education**

#### **Kwangwoon University**

Seoul, South Korea

MAJOR B.E. IN ELECTRONIC & COMMUNICATION ENGINEERING / MINOR B.E. IN DATA SCIENCE

Mar. 2014 - Feb. 2021 (Expected)

- Major GPA: 3.90 / 4.5 / Total GPA: 3.70 / 4.5
- Courses: Capstone Design I-II, AI & Speech Signal Processing, Software Design, Machine Learning, Computer Architecture, Operating System, Data Structure & Algorithm, Data Mining, Network Programming, IoT System Design, Big Data Language, Big Data Processing & Application, Database, Digital Signal Processing, Statistical application, Object-Oriented Programming, Object-Oriented Programming Practice, Open-Source Software, System Programming, C programming, Mobile Programming, Data Communication, Computer Network, Basic Electronic Circuit Experiment I-II, Electronic Circuit Theory I-II, Digital Logic, Phisics Electronic Technology, Engineering Math I-II, Probability and Irregular Signaling Theory, Probability and Statistics

## **Professional Experience**

**Kakao Brain** Pangyo, Gyunggi

Al Research Engineer

Nov. 2020 - Present

- Research & Develop Speech and Natural Language Processing fields
- Develop Natural Language Processing toolkit used to conduct various NLP tasks (e.g. ASR, NMT, TTS, ..., etc.)

**Kakao Brain** Pangyo, Gyunggi

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP Aug. 2020 - Nov. 2020

- Research & Develop English, Korean and Chinese Automatic Speech Recognition models
- Development of Multilingual Speech Synthesis Model with Support for 10 Languages

#### Spoken Language Lab @ Sogang

Undergraduate Researcher

Mapo, Seoul

Apr. 2020 - Aug. 2020

- Research End-to-End Automatic Speech Recognition Models
- Research Real-time Automatic Speech Recognition Based on Kaldi Toolkit

## **Research Interests**

**Speech** Speech Recognition, Speech Synthesis, Voice Activity Detection, Speech Enhancement

**NLP** Machine Translation, Language Model, Cross-lingual

**Software** Software Development, Software Architecture

## Skills

**Programming** Python, Java, C/C++, Shell Script, SQL, Android, Arduino, Assembly, HTML

**Deep Learning** PyTorch, Fairseq, PyTorch Lightning

**Data Analysis** Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn, NLTK

### **Publication**

2020 End-to-End Speech Recognition Models in English, Korean and Chinese, Bachelor's Graduation Thesis

2020 KoSpeech: Open-Source Toolkit for End-to-End Korean Speech Recognition, arXiv pre-print

November 14, 2020 Soohwan Kim · Résumé

# **Project Experience**

#### **Multilingual Speech Synthesis**

REPRESENTATIVE

Kakao Brain

Oct. 2020 - Nov. 2020

Representative

• Development of a speech synthesis model that supports 10 languages

• Supports for Voice-Cloning and Code-Switching

#### **English, Korean and Chinese ASR Models Development**

Kakao Brain

Aug. 2020 - Oct. 2020

• Development of English, Korean and Chinese Wav2vec 2.0 Models

- Experiment for improving the speed of inference
- · Comparative experiment on accuracy / inference speed by output-unit such as Character, Grapheme and Subword

#### KoSpeech: Open-Source Toolkit for End-to-End Korean Speech Recognition

Kwangwoon University

Jan. 2020 - Aug. 2020

AUTHOR

• Currently, over 100 people are stargazer this project [link]

• Write Technical Reports in arXiv [link]

# **Extracurricular Activity**

NLP Paper Reading

Kakao Brain

GROUP MEMBER Sep. 2020 - Present

- Kakao Brain Natural Language Processing Team's weekly paper reading study
- Reading a paper and summarizing its contents []link]

Technical Blog Naver Blog

WRITER Aug. 2018 - Present

- Technical posting of deep learning, programming, signal processing, paper review etc.
- Having more than 100 subscribers and an average of 200 visitors a day [link]

#### **Speech Recognition Study Group**

Kwangwoon University

Jan. 2020 - Mar. 2020

• Study speech signal processing (Spectrogram, Mel-Scale, MFCC etc ..)

• Reading a paper of speech recognition and recording its contents [link]

# **Teaching Experience**

## **Samsung AI Expert Course - Speech recognition**

Spoken Language Lab

TEACHING ASSISTANT

GROUP MEMBER

Jul. 2020 - Aug. 2020

• Conducted Teaching Assistant role in the Speech Recognition session

#### Object-Oriented Programming Practice

Kwangwoon University

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Mar. 2020 - Jun. 2020

- · Covered basic JAVA programming, Ran laboratories and had office hours every week.
- Answered students' questions in person and marked assignments

## **Awards & Honors**

#### **AWARDS**

2020.11 <b>1st Place, People's Choice Award</b> , Kwangwoon Eng	gineering Festival (President's Award)
---	--

2019.10 Finalist (12th Place), Naver A.I Hackathon - Speech

2019.09 Finalist, Kwangwoon University software start-up idea contest - Fall

2019.04 People's Choice Award, Kwangwoon University software start-up idea contest - Spring

2018.08 Excellence Award, Samsung Multi-Campus in Java-based Algorithm for SW Development

#### **Honors**

2020.03	<b>School Representative</b>	, 5G-based ICT	Convergence Service	e Idea Contest
---------	------------------------------	----------------	---------------------	----------------

2020.03 Excellent Scholarship, Samsong Scholarship

2019.03 Excellent Scholarship, Samsong Scholarship

2019.03 Academic Excellent Scholarship, Kwangwoon University

2018.09 Academic Excellent Scholarship, Kwangwoon University

2018.03 Academic Excellent Scholarship, Kwangwoon University